Guide to the African-Americans In Film: Collection Of Press Books, Campaign Books, Advertising Manuals, Etc., 1919-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Film titles L-R (Box 3)
  - Lifeboat, 1944. Danish souvenir program., (12mo, 8 p.)
    All original materials from Lifeboat are extremely uncommon. Canada Lee co-starred in this Hitchcock film from a script by John Steinbeck. Lee's performance is often cited by historians as an early case of a Black actor playing a non-stereotypical role in a major Hollywood film. Bogle II, p. 139: A Black steward, pensive and inarticulate, represents America's vast second-class citizenry. The role was played with somber dignity and intelligence by Canada Lee, the Broadway actor previously acclaimed for his work in the Orson Welles production of Native Son.
  - Lilies of the Field, 1963. Danish illustrated theater program., (12mo, 8 p.)
  - Lilies of the Field, 1963. Press book., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Sidney Poitier won Best Actor Oscar for his work in this film. Bogle, p. 135: Offered Poitier an opportunity to flex his muscles and be the ingratiating and dependable character he was so good at portraying.
  - Littlest Rebel, The, 1935., (8vo, 214 p.)
    Bill Bojangles Robinson. Willie Best. Robinson, the legendary dancer, appeared in not many films, and it is extremely difficult to find promotional materials on any of them. This Shirley Temple edition of the children's book The Littlest Rebel by Edward Peple (New York: Random House, 1959) has extensive illustrations of Robinson and other actors from the 1935 Shirley Temple film. [Physically removed from collection, cataloged individually and shelved at call no.: E #21351]
  - Long Ships, The, 1963., (Folio, 14 p., copyright 1974)
    Arguably the most peculiar role in Sidney Poitier's screen career, as a villainous Moor. Bogle II, p. 182: Poitier kidnaps a beautiful white woman [but] has been made to take a year's vow of celibacy. Therefore his sexual impulses remain safely suppressed.
  - Lost Man, The, 1969., (4to, 4 p., 10 leaves)
    Sidney Poitier. Bogle, p. 130-40: A group of Black militants, led by Poitier, out to commit a big payroll heist in order to get money for the family of a group of imprisoned 'brothers'...[Poitier] had attempted an image change, one more in keeping with the social temper of the time.
  - Lost Man, The, 1969. Advertising supplement., (4to, 3 p.)
  - Love Bug, The, 1919. Advertising flyer, (4 p.)
    Advertising flyer for four Norman Film Manufacturing Company Black-cast films suggested as a quadruple bill: The Love Bug ( 1919), The Crimson Skull ( 1921), The Green-Eyed Monster ( 1919) and The Bull-Dogger ( 1921).
  - L-Shaped Room, The, 1962. Press book insert, copyright 1964., (Folio, 2 p.)
  - L-Shaped Room, The, 1962. Press book, copyright 1963., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Brock Peters. Bogle II, p. 207: Even when cast as the homosexual West Indian Johnny in the British film The L-Shaped Room, [Peters'] characterizations had raw edge and bitter power.
  - L-Shaped Room, The, 1962. Press book insert, copyright 1963., (Folio, broadside)
  - Mack, The, 1977 reissue of 1973 film., (4to, 4 p.)
    Richard Pryor.
  - Malaga, 1962. Press book, copyright 1962., (Folio, 20 p.)
    Dorothy Dandridge in a British film. Bogle, p. 143-4: There is an unconscious documentary taking place within the movie: we become caught up in the personal tensions or drives of the actress herself rather than those of the character she is playing.
  - Malcolm X, 1972. Press book., (4to, 8 p. + 1 leaf)
    Feature-length documentary about the life of Malcolm X, given a very limited release by Warner Brothers, all materials from this film are extremely hard to find.
  - Malcolm X, 1992. Promotional book., (4to, 52 p.)
    The epic biography of Malcolm by Spike Lee. Deluxe special illustrated promotional book on the film, printed in small edition, profusely and richly illustrated.
  - Man, The, 1972. Press book, copyright 1971., (Folio, 8 p.)
    James Earl Jones. The first Black President of the United States. First they swore him in. Then they swore to get him.
  - Man Friday, 1975. Ad Supplement., (Folio, 6 p.)
    With special promotion for Black audiences.
  - Mandingo, 1975., (4to, 4 p.)
    Ken Norton. Brenda Sykes. Bogle, p. 147: A pulpy, lurid antebellum potboiler that turns the fantasy world of a romanticized film like Gone with the Wind inside out.
  - Mark of the Hawk, The, 1957., (Folio, 8 p., copyright 1958)
    Sidney Poitier. Eartha Kitt. Juano Hernandez. One of Poitier's early starring roles, and one of Kitt's few major screen roles. Bogle II, p. 180 and 188.
  - Marked For Death, 1990., (8vo, 4 p.)
    Basil Wallace.
  - McMasters, The, 1969., (Folio, 8 p. + 1 leaf)
    Brock Peters.
  - McMasters, The, 1969. British press book., (8vo, 6 + 2 p.)
  - Mean Mother, 1973., (Folio, 4 p. + 1 leaf)
    Clifton Brown.
  - Men in Black, 1997. Japanese promotional brochure., (4to, 32 p.)
    Will Smith.
  - Mission Impossible, 1996. Screening program., (4to, 4 p.)
    Ving Rhames.
  - Muthers, The, 1976., (8vo, 9 p.)
    Jeanne Bell. Jayne Kennedy.
  - Naked Gun 2 1/2, 1991. British press book., (8vo, 8 p.)
    O.J. Simpson.
  - Naked Prey, The, 1966., (Folio, 12 p.)
    Ken Gampu.
  - Naked Prey, The, 1966. British campaign book., (8vo, 4 p.)
  - Naked Prey, The, 1966. Promotional pamphlet., (8vo, 4 p.)
  - New Jack City, 1991. Japanese promotional brochure., (4to, 24 p.)
  - Norman Film Manufacturing Company
    An extraordinary group of promotional pieces, done in the silent era of the 1920s, by an enterprising company entirely devoted to Black-cast films. These Norman pieces give invaluable insight into the earliest decade of Black film making in this country. [See separate entries for: Black Gold ( 1927), Crimson Skull ( 1921), Flying Ace ( 1926), Love Bug, The ( 1919), Regeneration ( 1923)]
  - One More Time, 1970. Press book., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Sammy Davis, Jr.
  - Organization, The, 1971., (Folio, 4 p.)
  - Paris Blues, 1961. Press book., (Folio, 12 p., covers detached but present)
    Sidney Poitier. Diahann Carroll. Bogle, p. 161-2: Two expatriate jazz musicians, one white (Newman), the other Black (Poitier), each living in Paris, meet two vacationing American women (Joanne Woodward and Diahann Carroll). One pertinent issue arises: should Poitier's character remain in Paris (where it appears he does not have to contend with racial biases) or should he return to the States to fight his battles there?
  - Police Academy, 1984. British press book., (8vo, 6 p.)
    Michael Winslow. Bubba Smith.
  - Porgy and Bess, 1959.
    Sidney Poitier and Dorothy Dandridge star in this folk opera by George Gershwin with lyrics by DuBose Heyward and Ira Gershwin. The profusely illustrated 36-page volume The Samuel Goldwyn Motion Picture Production of Porgy and Bess (New York: Random House, 1959) includes cast bios. [Physically removed from collection, cataloged individually and shelved at call no.: E q#2175]
  - Pressure Point, 1962. Press book., (Folio, 12 p.)
  - Quadroon, 1972., (Folio, 8 p., copyright 1971)
    Rare early Blaxploitation film, this one set in 1835 New Orleans.
  - Quadroon, 1972. Promotional flyer., (Broadside)
  - Rainbow Bridge, 1972. Press book., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Jimi Hendrix.
  - Regeneration, 1923., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Romance in Southern Seas featuring Stella Mayo, Sensational Colored Screen Beauty. All-Colored Cast, contains a detailed list of proposed upcoming production and text emphasizing that Norman is the only Company making Colored Pictures that owns and operates its own studio and laboratory.
  - Riot, 1969. Press book., (4to, 10 p.)
    Jim Brown. Bogle II, p. 220: Jim Brown suggested violence and power, a dash and daring never before exhibited by a Black man [in a film]...He was big. He was Black. He was outspoken. He was baaaadddd.
  - Riot, 1969. Promotional booklet The Prison Record., (8vo, 4 p.)
  - Robin and the 7 Hoods, 1964. Press book., (Folio, 28 p.)
    Sammy Davis Jr. in one of the famous Rat Pack films with Frank Sinatra, Dean Martin, et al. Bogle II, p. 214-5: On the surface the clan pictures were egalitarian affairs; underneath they rotted from white patronizing and hypocrisy.
  - Rock Baby, Rock It, 1957., (4to, 4 p.)
    B-movie rock musical showcased calypso group the Five Stars.
  - Rock Baby, Rock It, 1957. Promotional flyer, (8vo, broadside)
  - Rocky III, 1982. Advertising supplement., (8vo, 8 p.)
- Film titles S-Z (Box 4)
  - St. Louis Blues, 1958. Theatre program., (8vo, 4 p.)
    Eartha Kitt. Nat King Cole. Ruby Dee. Ella Fitzgerald. Cab Calloway. Pearl Bailey. Mahalia Jackson. Theatre program from Germany, with an elegant photomontage of images from the film. Bogle, p. 204: The life of Black composer W.C. Handy, Hollywood style.
  - Sam Whiskey, 1969. Press book., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Ossie Davis.
  - Sapphire, 1959., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Rare film about Afro-British life, a mystery about a young woman attempting to pass.
  - Save the Children, 1973. Press book., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Jesse Jackson. Sammy Davis Jr. The Chi-Lites. Nancy Wilson. The Temptations. Concert film from the 1972 Operation PUSH exposition in Chicago, interspersed with documentary footage of the period. Bogle, pp. 182-3.
  - Save the Children, 1973. Advertising sheets., (6 leaves)
  - Scalphunters, The, 1968. Advertising supplement (#2), (Folio, 4 p.)
  - Scream, Blacula, Scream, 1973. British press book., (8vo, 2 p.)
  - Scream, Blacula, Scream, 1973., (4to, 16 p.)
    William Marshall. Horror sequel.
  - Seizure, 1974. Press book., (Folio, 9 leaves)
    Henry Baker.
  - Shaft, 1971. Press book., (Folio, 12 p.)
    One of the legendary films which launched the Blaxploitation film cycle of the 1970s. Bogle, p. 185: [Director Gordon] Parks' strong identification with Shaft as a slick, pretty, sexy, dude gives the picture unexpected heat and zip.
  - Shaft in Africa, 1973. Press book., (4to, 14 p.)
    Richard Roundtree. Second and last sequel of this popular series.
  - Shaft's Big Score!, 1972. Press book., (4to, 16 p.)
    Director Gordon Parks and Richard Roundtree teamed up again for this first sequel. Bogle, p. 186.
  - Shaft's Big Score!, 1972. Press book., (4to, 16 p., copy 2)
  - Shock Corridor, 1963. Promotional brochure., (4to, 4 p.)
  - Silver Streak, 1976. Press book., (8vo, 16 leaves)
    The first of a very successful series of comedies pairing Richard Pryor and Gene Wilder.
  - Skin Game, 1971. Press book., (4to, 10 p. + 1 broadside)
    Lou Gossett, Jr. Bogle, p. 191: A pre-Civil War con man comes up with an ingenious con game: he repeatedly sells his Black partner (Gossett) in one slave town to one simpleton slave owner after another. After each sale, Gossett quickly escapes, teaming up with [James] Garner for yet another sale.
  - Slams, The, 1973. Press book., (4to, 12 p.)
    Jim Brown. Judy Pace.
  - Slaughter's Big Rip-Off, 1973., (4to, 20 p.)
    Jim Brown. Brock Peters. Bogle, p. 192: Gaudy sequel to the gaudy original [ Slaughter, 1972]...As in the first, Brown's a sepia Superman, again almost single-handedly taking on the mob.
  - Slaves, The, 1969., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Dionne Warwick. Ossie Davis. Official entry 1969 Cannes Film Festival. Bogle, p. 192: Ponderous high times in the Old South. This was an early attempt to reach the, then new, evolving Black movie audience.
  - Slender Thread, The, 1965., (4to, 20 p.)
  - Soul of Nigger Charley, 1973. Press book., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Fred Williamson. Bogle, p. 198.
  - Soul of Nigger Charley, 1973. Advertising sheets., (4 leaves)
  - Soul Soldier, 1970., (Folio, 8 p., copyright 1971)
    Very early entry in the Blaxploitation cycle starring athlete Rafer Johnson. Bogle, p. 242.
  - Soul to Soul, 1971. Press book., (4to, 8 leaves)
    Roberta Flack. Wilson Pickett. Voices of East Harlem. Bogle, p. 199: A return-to-the-motherland kind of documentary, focusing on an all-night 15-hour soul concert performed in Ghana during a week-long celebration of that nation's independence.
  - Sparkle, 1976., (4to, 5 p.)
    Irene Cara. Lonette McKee. Bogle, p. 201: One of Black America's first cult films. The movie follows the rise and fall of three Harlem sisters who, guided by two boyfriends, form a singing group in the late 1950s.
  - Split, The, 1968. Campaign book., (Folio, 12 p.)
    Jim Brown. Diahann Carroll.
  - Stormy Weather, 1943. Souvenir program., (12mo, 8 p.)
    Famous wartime musical which made use of an astonishing virtual who's who of top African-American talents. Lena Horne. Fats Waller. The Nicholas Brothers. Cab Calloway. Bill Robinson. All promotional materials from this film are extremely scarce. This is a nicely illustrated souvenir program from Denmark.
  - Sugar Hill, 1974., (4to, 16 p.)
    Marki Bey. Bogle, p. 208.
  - Super Fly, 1972. Press book., (4to, 12 + 1 p. + review ad supplement, 2 p.)
    Ron O'Neal. Bogle, p. 208: A very successful, controversial film centering on a Harlem cocaine dealer [O'Neal], who wants out of the drug business. The basic plot was to be repeated in scores of other blaxploitation films.
  - Super Fly T.N.T., 1973. Press book., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Ron O'Neal in a sequel.
  - Super Fly T.N.T., 1973. Advertising sheets., (6 leaves)
  - Swashbuckler, 1976. Advertising supplement, copyright 1976., (8vo, 5 leaves)
  - Sweet Jesus Preacher Man, 1973. Press book., (4to, 8 p.)
    Roger E. Mosely.
  - Sweet Sweetback's Baadasssss Song, 1971. Press book., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Melvin Van Peebles (director). [This is an extremely rare press book, all original materials from this film seem to have vanished a long time ago.] Bogle, p. 210-211: It may be difficult for a contemporary audience to understand the extreme impact of this historic, legendary movie...But before its appearance, Black characters, in sentimental films that sought to promote the idea that things could work out between Black and white, were always tame and manageable without any sexual or political defiance. Sweetback, however, not only took the wraps off a Black man's sexuality...but was also an open declaration of war on white America.
  - Take A Hard Ride, 1975. Ad supplement., (4to, 4 p.)
  - Teenage Millionaire, 1962. Press book, copyright 1961., (4to, 8 p.)
    Jackie Wilson. Chubby Checker.
  - That Man Bolt, 1973. Press book, copyright 1973., (8vo, 12 leaves)
  - That Man Bolt, 1973. Advertising supplement, copyright 1974., (8vo, 3 leaves)
  - That's the Way of the World, 1975. Press book, copyright 1976., (Folio, 6 p.)
    Earth, Wind, and Fire.
  - They Call Me Mister Tibbs, 1970. Press book., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Sidney Poitier. Sequel to In the Heat of the Night ( 1967)
  - Three the Hard Way, 1974., (4to, 12 p.)
    Action film starring Jim Brown, Fred Williamson, and Jim Kelly. Directed by Gordon Parks, Jr.
  - Tick...Tick...Tick, 1970., (Folio, 12 p.)
    Jim Brown. [A small area of blank margin to one leaf is missing, with no content affected]. Bogle, p. 217: Film marks the Jim Brown movie hero's full ascension into the ranks of the American establishment.
  - To Kill A Mockingbird, 1967 reissue of 1962 film., (4to, 4 leaves, copyright 1967)
    Brock Peters. Reissue on a double bill with, of all the possible unlikely choices, a Doris Day comedy.
  - To Sir, with Love, 1966., (Folio, 16 p., copyright 1966)
    Sidney Poitier. Bogle, p. 218: Strangely enough, in an era of political unrest among the young of America, this tame, lightweight apolitical fantasy seemed to enchant audiences of all ages--and colors--and soon it was evident as well that the most popular star in America was Sidney Poitier. In other films, Poitier had proven himself as an actor. Now he was proven box office.
  - To Sir, with Love, 1966. Advertising press book insert, copyright 1967., (Folio, 4 p.)
    Multiple-run and hold over advertising press book insert.
  - Top of the Heap, 1972., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Christopher St. John (also producer, writer, and director). Early entry in the Blaxploitation cycle. Bogle II, p. 241.
  - Topaz, 1969. Advertising booklet., (4to, 4 p., 4 leaves)
    Roscoe Lee Browne in Hitchcock suspense film.
  - Topaz, 1969. Advertising sheets., (4to, 6 leaves)
  - Towering Inferno, The, 1974. Press book, copyright 1975., (4to, 20 p.)
  - Toy, The, 1982. Special advertising printout., (Large Folio, 2 leaves)
  - Trouble Man, 1972., (4to, 12 p.)
    Robert Hooks. Paula Kelly. Bogle, p. 222.
  - Truck Turner, 1974., (4to, 20 p.)
    Isaac Hayes. Bogle, p. 223.
  - Truck Turner, 1974. Promotional newsletter., (4to, 4 p.)
    Isaac Hayes. Special promotional piece in the form of a newsletter, International Bail Bond News.
  - Truck Turner, 1974. Press book., (8vo, 4 leaves)
    Special press book for a double-bill release with Foxy Brown (1974).
  - Twilight Zone-The Movie, 1983. British campaign book., (8vo, 6 p.)
    Scatman Crothers.
  - Two Gentlemen Sharing, 1969., (Folio, 8 p.)
    Hal Frederick. Esther Anderson. Unusual but sensationally-treated story of mixed race couples.
  - Uptight!, 1968., (4to, 12 p.)
    Ruby Dee. Roscoe Lee Browne. Bogle, p. 224: The first American film to spotlight Black 'revolutionaries' and the separatist movement of the 1960s.
  - Warm December, A, 1973. Press book., (4to, 12 p. + fashion mat broadside)
    Sidney Poitier. Bogle, p. 226-7: Part Love Story...part Roman Holiday...it was too bourgeois for some tastes and often too tame and wholesome for its own good. Yet when shown on television today, it runs more smoothly and proves itself rather likable: one of the very few romantic films with Black stars.
  - Watermelon Man, 1970. Press book insert., (4to, 2 p.)
  - Watusi, 1959., (Folio, 12 p.)
    The venerable actor Rex Ingram played the role of Umbopa. Bogle II, p. 70: Ingram was frequently compared to Paul Robeson. Both men presented immensely dignified and self-contained Black male characters. Yet there were differences. Although Ingram was not as good an actor as Robeson, nor as heroic a presence, he was able to express the one thing Robeson lacked: a gentleness, an overriding interest and sympathy in all of mankind.
  - Watusi, 1959. Promotional booklet., (8vo, 4 p.)
  - Winterhawk, 1976., (4to, 4 p., 4 leaves)
    Woody Strode.
  - Woodstock, 1970., (Folio, 22 p.)
    Legendary rock musical showcases Sly and the Family Stone, Richie Havens, and, of course, Jimi Hendrix.
  - World, The Flesh and the Devil, The, 1959. Press book., (Folio, 20 p.)
    Harry Belafonte. Science-fiction film in which Belafonte is one of only three survivors of a nuclear holocaust, produced by Belafonte. Bogle II, p. 191.
  - World's Greatest Athlete, The, 1973. Ad pad., (4to, 9 leaves)
  - Wusa, 1970., (4to, 6 p.)
    Moses Gunn.
  - Zircon, 1920., (4to, 4 p.)
    Flyer for unproduced film serial of the 1920s featuring 15 chapters. Also features advertisements for films "Regeneration," "The Crimson Skull," "Green Eyed Monster," and "The Bull Dogger."